# Mauro Lepore

maurolepore@gmail.com | + 1 346 773 2738

I am an ecologist turned software engineer and data science consultant. I now work for a network of forest ecologists, building R packages and passionately sharing resources with the researchers and students I support. I also have several years of experience teaching, and providing both community and customer services.

### **EXPERIENCE**

### Software engineer, data science consultant

2017-08 - present

ForestGEO

National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution, Washington DC, USA

My official title is "IT specialist - R-package developer". In practice, I build software, learn best practices in data science, and share ideas and resources with researchers and higher-education students to help them work in an efficient, transparent, and reproducible way. I spend most of my time building R packages or teaching R, Git, GitHub, sometimes in person but mostly remotely.

#### Data science instructor (volunteer)

The Carpentries

2018 - present

- Texas A&M University-Kingsville
- National Museum of Natural History, Smithsonian Institution
- Smithsonian Environmental Research Center, Smithsonian Institution

As a certified instructor of The Carpentries, I occasionally teach and help teach foundational coding and data science skills to researchers (e.g. Excel, OpenRefine, SQL, R).

#### Postdoctoral research fellow

2016-02 to 2017-06

O'Dea Lab: Change and Variation in Tropical Seas

Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute, Panama City, Panama

I researched how coral reefs varied and changed through time, before and since human impacts. I supervised two wonderful interns (one undergraduate and one postgraduate student).

### Teaching university students

Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute

2016-12

Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute, Bocas del Toro Research Station, Panama

Teaching assistant for university students from Texas A&M University (GEOS405) during a five-days long field-based research. Responsible for delivering lectures, mentoring research projects, boating and snorkeling safety, logistics in English and Spanish.

### Teaching university students

The University of Queensland 2012-04 - 2014-11

- St Lucia, Brisbane, Australia
- Moreton Bay Research Station, North Stradbroke Island, Australia
- Heron Island Research Station, Heron Island, Australia

Teaching assistant in classroom, lab, and field settings for resident students of The University of Queensland (MARS2014, MARS2005); also for international students from Stanford University, and the University of California. Responsible for marking assignments, delivering short lectures, mentoring research projects, boating and snorkeling safety, and logistics.

#### Teaching high school students

The University of Queensland 2011-04 - 2015-06

- Moreton Bay Research Station, North Stradbroke Island, Australia
- St Lucia, Brisbane, Australia

Lecturer and demonstrator during science camps for high school students doing lab- and field-based research. Also responsible for liaising with school teachers and training less experienced demonstrators.

### Customer service (photographer)

Foto Paleo, Concepto RD, Tropical Pictures, Black & White, event photography.com, and more 1999 - 2016

Argentina, Dominican Republic, Spain, Australia

During most of my adult life I have been a freelance photographer, mostly of people. As a tourists photographer I learned to be persuasive, and to consolidate sales of intangible products which cost is difficult to measure. And as a weddings photographer I learned to build trusted relationships and a deep understanding of my customers' needs. Also I learned to be a good problem-solver in stressful conditions, and very patient with difficult customers.

#### Comunity service (life guard)

Municipalidad del Partido de la Costa 1999 - 2010 Santa Teresita, Buenos Aires, Argentina

For about a decade I spent my summers working as a life guard. On this job I learned the importance of community service. I also learned to invest in strong relationships with my colleagues, to ask for help, and to be reliable.

#### Outreach

Museo Argentino de Ciencias Naturales, Argentina 2003-07 - 2003-12 and 2004-04 - 2004-08 Parque Centenario, Buenos Aires, Argentina

Responsible for explaining exhibitions to engage people of all ages.

### **EDUCATION**

#### The University of Queensland, Australia

PhD, Ecology, Environmental Sciences, Geochemistry 2011-2015

School of Biological Sciences, ARC Center of Excellence for Coral Reef Studies

Thesis: "Long term dynamics of coral reefs in the inshore southern Great Barrier Reef".

I examined three issues:

- 1. The potential of a reef system to constitute a refuge for coral reefs from global warming.
- 2. The accretion rate of the reef flat and reef slope environment through time.
- 3. Changes in coral community structure through time, and the mechanisms of community assembly.

I supervised three students and 20 volunteers, both in the field and lab.

#### Universidad de Buenos Aires, Argentina

Licentiate degree, Biological Sciences, Marine Ecology 1999-2008 Faculty of Natural Sciences

Thesis: "Estudio del crecimiento de la almeja amarilla Argentina Mesodesma mactroides por marcaje fluorescente in situ y comparación con el método de análisis de distribuciones de frecuencias de tallas".

I compared a novel and traditional method to study the growth rate of a clam.

## **CERTIFICATIONS**

#### Instructor of The Carpentries

The Carpentries 2018-06 Credential http://bit.ly/2TRE8M5

#### **SKILLS**

# Industry knowledge

Computer software, higher education, data science, statistics, teaching, research.

# Tools & technologies

- R programming for data science (e.g. tidyverse packages, rmarkdown, shiny), Q&A (e.g. testthat), and software engineering (e.g. usethis, rlang, devtools, roxygen2), using both functional programming and object-oriented (e.g. S3) paradigms
- Bash and Git for version control
- GitHub for collaboration and project management
- TravisCI for continuous integration, and for automatically building and deploying websites and R packages

## **LANGUAGES**

English (full professional) and Spanish (native).

#### **PROJECTS**

## tor: Import Multiple Files From a Single Directory at Once

2019-01 - present

URL https://CRAN.R-project.org/package=tor

The goal of tor (to-R) is to help you to import multiple files from a single directory at once, and to do so as quickly, flexibly, and simply as possible.

# fgeo: Analyze Forest Diversity and Dynamics

2017-08 - present

URL https://forestgeo.github.io/fgeo/

'fgeo' is a collection of R packages to analyze forest diversity and dynamics. It includes packages to manipulate and plot ForestGEO data, and to do common analyses including abundance, demography, and species-habitats associations.

### PEER-REVIEWED PUBLICATIONS

2017

Look to the past for an optimistic future A O'dea, EM Dillon, AH Altieri, ML Lepore Conservation Biology 31 (6), 1221-1222

2015

Long-Term Dynamics of Coral Reefs in the Inshore Southern Great Barrier Reef

ML Lepore (supervisors: J Pandolfi and JX Zhao)

PhD thesis. School of Biological Sciences, The University of Queensland

2011

Population structure, growth and production of the yellow clam *Mesodesma mactroides* (Bivalvia: Mesodesmatidae) from a high-energy, temperate beach in northern Argentina

M Herrmann, JEF Alfaya, ML Lepore, PE Penchaszadeh, WE Arntz.

Helgoland Marine Research 65 (3), 285

2009

Aplicación de calceína para la estimación del crecimiento de la almeja amarilla *Mesodesma mactroides* Reeve, 1854

ML Lepore, PE Penchaszadeh, F Alfaya, E José, M Herrmann

Revista de biología marina y oceanografía 44 (3), 767-774

2009

Growth estimations of the Argentinean wedge clam *Donax hanleyanus*: A comparison between length-frequency distribution and size-increment analysis

M Herrmann, ML Lepore, J Laudien, WE Arntz, PE Penchaszadeh

Journal of Experimental Marine Biology and Ecology 379 (1-2), 8-15

2009

Reproductive cycle and gonad development of the Northern Argentinean Mesodesma mactroides (Bivalvia:

Mesodesmatidae) M Herrmann, JEF Alfaya, ML Lepore, PE Penchaszadeh, J Laudien Helgoland Marine Research 63 (3), 207

#### 2008

Estudio del crecimiento de la almeja amarilla argentina *Mesodesma mactroides* por marcaje fluorescente in situ y comparación con el método de análisis de distribuciones de frecuencias de tallas ML Lepore (supervisors: M Herrmann, PE Penchaszadeh)

Licentiate thesis. Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Universidad de Buenos Aires